PARTH SATISH AMRAPURKAR

980-205-5536 | pamrapurkar@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/parthsa

SUMMARY

Mechanical Engineer with a master's degree and 3+ years of experience in product design and development. Experience in product development (concept, prototyping to manufacturing, and realization). Proficient in project management, CAD, CAE - FEA & CFD, 3D printing, and manufacturing with extensive technical knowledge. Proven record of creating costeffective designs through integrating DFM, DFA & DFMEA techniques. Excellent communicator with a record of saving costs by negotiating contracts with suppliers and customers. Skilled to work in a collaborative environment.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Product Design | CAD | Blueprints | SolidWorks | 3D Modeling | FEA - ANSYS, ABAQUS | CFD - FLOEFD | GD&T ASME Y14.5 2009 | 3D printing | Troubleshooting | PTC CREO | MATLAB | Six Sigma | Python | CATIA V5 - Part design, Surfacing, cavity core, part simulation, assembly | MATLAB | RCA | SPC | AutoCAD | MS Office | Bill of Material | DFA | DFM.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Engineer - Product design and innovation Stanley Black and Decker, MD, USA

April 2021 - Present

- Designing a fan blower ground-up with 75% power savings, 2x output, and projected sales of over 150k/yr. units.
- Designed first in world concept of a track saw track reducing shipping space by 80% and waste by more than 25%.
- Carried out tolerance stack-up analysis for designed components and assemblies.
- Performed ray-tracing analysis of **LED** modules on smart speakers on Trace-pro software.
- Designed Spyder-kicker and verified the design using FEA structural analysis for smart speaker line.
- Performed **CFD** analysis to verify the flow pattern, temperature, pressure of fan systems.
- Utilized **DFM**, and **DFA** techniques to design injection molded and aluminum extruded products.
- Developed project timelines and stages from concept planning execution performance closure stages.
- Collaborated with industrial design, marketing, software, and testing departments.

Design Engineer I

Caterpillar, Lafayette, IN, USA

February 2021 – March 2021

- Designing of mounts, fixtures, and components required for installation of 35L to 105L oil and gas engines.
- Utilized PTC Creo for parametric 3D modeling of the designs and to create 2D drawings with proper GD&T.
- Achieved 80% file reduction by creating installation drawings to meet the client's needs.

Graduate Research Assistant

UNC Charlotte, Charlotte, NC, USA

October 2018 - January 2021

- Developed a model for SLS metal 3D printing using SolidWorks for CAD and DEM for computation model.
- Implemented the design of experiments (DOE) to prioritize the study of different process parameters using Minitab and saved 80% in computation time and costs. Prepared technical documentation for each step of the project.
- Automated post-processing scripts on Python for analyzing and visualizing the extracted raw data.
- Analyzed normal distribution/ bell curve of data to analyze in which SD the majority of the data/ values fall.
- Developed Finite element model for analyzing gas arc welding process using Abaqus & Fortran software on HPC.

Design and Manufacturing Engineering Intern

May 2019 - August 2019

- nVent, Aberdeen, NC, USA
- Incorporated laser length encoders achieving length accuracy up to 10 microns and waste reduction by 20%.
- Designed fixtures enclosures to hold high-precision lasers, performed heat dissipation analysis to confirm designs.
- Developed test protocols for new material testing. Performed troubleshooting of mechanical & electrical systems.
- Sourced new suppliers and negotiated contracts that saved more than 15% of costs for machinery.
- Incorporated vacuum system as the **5S** measure on manufacturing lines that saved **20%** in labor costs.

Design and Manufacturing Engineer

Badve Engineering, MH, India

- Led a team for the design of a sheet metal forming press tool that increased muffler production by 37%.
- Created ECNs, BOMs, and work instructions and released designs and drawings using Windchill software.
- Utilized **SPC** to pick point outliers in manufacturing data, applied **RCA** and **FMEA** to optimize the process.
- Used CATIA V5 for modeling punch and die system and 2D drawings with ASME Y14.5 2009 standards.

Manufacturing Engineer trainee

May 2017 - June 2017

July 2017 - July 2018

HONDA Motors, KA, India

- Identified and analyzed the in-process gap in body fender bolt's torque measurements vs compliance.
- Facilitated Kaizen Rapid Improvement Events (RIEs), implemented improvements using Six Sigma principles.

EDUCATION

University of North Carolina at Charlotte

May 2020

Master of Science (M.S) in Mechanical Engineering

GPA - 3.44 / 4.0

Savitribai Phule Pune University

July 2018

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E) in Mechanical Engineering

GPA - 3.57 / 4.0

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

Axial fan blower, Stanley black, and decker

August 2021 - Present

- Individually designed a FAN for job site blower. Performed parametric CFD analysis to study how different parameters of the fan affect the efficiency, horsepower, power usage, CFM output of the FAN.
- Planned the project from the ground up, designed injection molded components for the fan system.
- Temperature control system for 3D printer PID control, UNC Charlotte

August 2019 - December 2019

- Built a PID control system using Arduino to control an Aluminum block extruder used in an FDM 3D printer.
- Developed a code in Arduino C++ to connect the heater, fan, MOSFET, LCD screen displaying the temperature with one another to communicate for temperature control.
- Temperature analysis of a plate, UNC Charlotte

October 2018 - December 2018

- Performed a temperature analysis study of a 2D plate by developing a **MATLAB** code from scratch.
- Adopted implicit and explicit methods along with ADI code implementation to simulate and study temperature variation in the model. Analyzed the results by creating temperature evolution 3D graphs.

CERTIFICATIONS & CONFERENCE

- Discrete Element Modeling of Scraping Process and Quantification of Powder Bed Quality for SLM, ASME 2020 15th IMSEC (https://asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/MSEC/proceedings-abstract/MSEC2020/V001T01A037/1095621)
- GD&T and Engineering Drawings (LinkedIn)
- Design for Additive Manufacturing and 3D printer troubleshooting (LinkedIn)
- Rapid prototyping for Product Design (LinkedIn)

LEADERSHIP

Teaching assistant / Class head for 70+ students teaching applied physics experiments.

Jan 19 - May 20

Led a team of 10 for organizing technical events in CAD using CATIA and SolidWorks.

Jun 15 - Jan 18

HOBBIES

Designing components for self-use and 3D printing them | DIY | Photography | Hiking | Reading.